all right
[Music]
there appears to be a significant
protective effect of a vegetarian diet
for heart disease and all cancers
combined particularly for those eating
vegan but that's for total cancer what
about breast cancer and prostate cancer
specifically
it's been about a half dozen studies on
breast cancer risk and various
plant-based dietary patterns and they
all found lower risk as expected
in some studies vegetarians had less
than half the odds of breast cancer
compared to non-vegetarians suggesting
vegetarian diets show a protective role
against breast cancer risk in another
study eating a non-vegetarian diet was
one of the most important risk factors
nearly tripling the odds of breast
cancer and the California teachers study
a more plant-based pattern was
associated with significant reduction in
breast cancer risk as well so even
trending in that direction towards a
greater consumption of for example
fruits and vegetables is associated with
reduced breast cancer risk particularly
for the hardest to treat tumors which is
interesting a potential Avenue for
prevention
some of the reductions in Risk were only
statistically significant if you
included the weight loss benefits of
plant-based eating and Associated
lifestyle factors and other reductions
of risk not statistically significant
regardless lower risk but not
significant lower risk but not
significant meaning like in half of
these days the lower risk may have just
been you know statistical flukes by
chance
okay but this for example was for
vegetarians do vegan women do any better
vegetarian diets seem to offer
protection from cancers of the
gastrointestinal tract whereas vegan
diet seemed to confer lower risk of all
cancers put together and female specific
cancers in particular which included
breast cancer but also included cervical
endometrial and ovarian cancer after a
few more years they were able to tease
out the breast cancer data and vegan
showed consistently lower risk estimates
but not statistically significantly so
one study in India even suggested that
vegetarians who eat eggs have lower risk
than vegetarians who don't but put all
the studies on egg intake and breast
cancer together and eating like one egg
a day five or more eggs a week appears
to increase breast cancer risk compared
to not eating any eggs at all
an increase of five eggs a week was also
associated with a 47 increase in fatal
prostate cancer in general if you look
at the effect of plant and animal-based
Foods on prostate cancer risk most
studies showed that plant-based foods
are associated with either decreased or
neutral risk of prostate cancer whereas
animal-based Foods particularly dairy
products are associated with either
increase or neutral risk the dairy and
eggs may be why all three studies on
prostate cancer in vegans found
decreased risk but half of the
vegetarian studies show no change it's
not just about avoiding meat though
vegetables and beans specifically were
also associated with lower risk and the
same with breast cancer High intakes of
vegetables and pulses like beans lentils
and chickpeas were associated with
protection against breast cancer we're
talking like half the odds of breast
cancer eating four more vegetable
additions a day or a daily serving of
beans or lentils regardless of whether
you eat meat no this is one of the
studies that only showed a
non-statistically significant drop in
Risk among vegetarians so it may be
better to be a meat eater who eats lots
of Greens and Beans compared to a
vegetarian who instead eats lots of junk
now diet recommendations should go
beyond just pushing a specific array of
foods and really just promote the
overall benefits of eating more whole
plant Foods in general but what happens
if you do just push more veggies you
don't know until you put it to the test
effective a behavioral intervention to
increase vegetable consumption on cancer
progression among men with early stage
prostate cancer oh that's exciting
trying increased vegetable intake to not
just prevent but treat cancer men with
biopsy proven prostate cancer were
randomized to an encouragement to eat
seven or more servings of vegetables a
day nice and the control group was just
given some generic dietary info
and among men with early stage prostate
cancer under active surveillance a
behavioral intervention that increased
vegetable consumption did not
significantly reduce the risk of
prostate cancer progression ah bummer
but wait a second the trial wasn't
testing increased vegetable consumption
but the effect of advice the more
vegetables did they actually do it
the behavioral intervention this study
produced robust sustained increases in
vegetable intake for two years the
researchers wrote but alas still didn't
work
at the end of those two years they were
eating two more servings wait just two
not seven and so the difference between
the vegetable group and the control
group was less than two servings they
were also supposed to get at least two
servings of tomatoes a day and two
servings of broccoli type cruciferous
vegetables every day yet ended up only
eating about an ounce of cruciferous and
less than a tenth of a serving of
tomatoes so with so little dietary
change it's no wonder there was so
little change in the cancer though it's
possible you also have to cut down on
animal Foods in this three-month study
for men who had prostate cancer come
back after surgery and radiation they
were able to boost plant Foods restrict
animal Foods actually eat some more
tomatoes and the average PSA doubling
time meaning how fast the tumor is
growing slowed from about 22 months to
59 months so doubling in less than two
years to then taking nearly five years
all just from a three-month dietary
intervention whereas the control group
didn't change now slowing down a
tumorous nice but how about reversing
its growth or shrinking it down
our strict vegetarians protected against
prostate cancer yes those eating
strictly plant-based diets have only a
fraction of the risk of getting in the
first place but that's not the half of
it yes the ornish study we talked about
this before notable in my how not to die
from cancer video a randomized men with
prostate cancer to a diet pact with
fruits vegetables whole grains and beans
and tumors on average appeared to shrink
as noted by PSA trending down while the
control group's cancer continued to grow
and drip some blood from the plant-based
group on some prostate cancer growing in
a Petri dish and the plant-based blood
suppress the cancer growth almost eight
times better and the more they stuck to
their diet the more their bloodstream
suppressed the cancer growth
[Music]
thank you